[music] The best thing I can do is give
this person some sort of context and it
will tell us why the crime was committed
[music]
i.e. motive.
>> I think the chemistry is telling us that
this [music] person is playing a very
careful political and religious game.
>> And you think there's all this political
upheaval going on in ancient Egypt and
it's [music] encapsulated in a a tiny
sample the size of a pin head.
Just because they're 3,000 years old
doesn't mean that we can't [music] apply
modern forensics and come up with good
answers.
>> I'm far from convinced that's going to
be an easy job.
>> It feels like it's doing more damage, if
you see what I mean.
>> This is [music] a really exciting find
and a brilliant result for this sort of
experimental archaeology.
>> [music]
[music]
>> in Bolton Museum in the north of England
lies a unique mummy partially unwrapped
yet [music] spectacularly preserved
after 3 millennia. Her identity shrouded
in mystery. Her cause of death lost to
[music] history.
>> This is a a great mummy. Fantastic
preservation.
>> The uh coffin and mummy have be are
probably our two most popular pieces in
the Egyptian gallery. And you can see
why.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> It's a beautiful coffin. A number of
people have studied [music] it in great
detail. We know it's a very fine example
of its period. We know who it was made
for and [music]
what the owner was.
>> Yeah. There's a lovely image there of
the the person it was made for.
Obviously, a lady of very high status in
a fine linen [music] robes and and
lovely wig.
>> Yeah. And you can see just she's making
an offering to a deity. [music] And then
here on a panel of inscription, you've
got her her name and title. She's the
lady of the house, the [music] chantress
of Ammun Ray, king of the gods, and
here's her name, Tau Henut. So, we know
who she was and what she did. [music]
>> One thing I have noticed, it does seem
to be an incredibly tight fit um for the
the person [music] within. So, I'd be a
little concerned that when this was
actually completely wrapped, [music]
>> I can't see how this person would have
fitted inside this coffin.
>> You can really see where the shoulders
are brushing against the sides of the
coffin. The mummy, as you say, would
have been a good deal fatter when it was
intact.
>> There's definitely something suspicious
[music] here. Uh, we need to get the
mummy out so we can have a a good look.
>> Dr. Joanne [music] Fletcher's mission is
to take this misfit mummy, bring it to
life, and then find out how that [music]
life came to its end.
She is one of Britain's foremost
Egyptologists and a world authority on
mummies. The grime of centuries could
hide any number of secrets from a casual
observer. But Joanne is anything [music]
but casual.
>> Beautifully preserved earlobe.
Absolutely superb. And the teeth, the
teeth are really quite extraordinary
because although there's some chipping
there, what you're actually seeing
very distinctly [music] here is a is an
overjet of the upper set of teeth, which
is a very unusual feature.
The initial physical [music] inspection
is crucial.
In her work, the tiniest details [music]
often provide the vital clue as to how
someone lived or died.
Together with her team of elite
scientists, Dr. Fletcher has
investigated mummies on almost every
continent.
[music] This is going to be a tough case
for the mummy investigation team.
Dr. Steven Buckley is one of the world's
top archaeological chemists. He uses
cuttingedge techniques from the world of
chemical research to identify substances
in, on, and around mummies. [music]
Duncan Lees is a forensic archaeologist
specializing in high-tech survey
techniques. His forensic expertise means
he's called in to investigate modern
crime scenes all over the world.
Jill Scott is an Egyptologist and an
expert in the preservation and
conservation of mummies. [music] Her
research skills and wealth of
archaeological knowledge make her
perfect as the team's archive and
background researcher for the
investigation.
The challenge is now on. The team may
have the tools of modern forensics, but
with little information to go on,
they'll need all their investigative
skills [music] to unlock this ancient
mystery.
Dr. Fletcher's briefing gives the team a
starting point for the investigation.
The coffin apparently has been studied
by quite a lot of academics over the
years. They know plenty uh about the the
woman it was made for. You can see it's
it's beautiful colors. Uh this is the
lady herself. She was a priestess. So
you can imagine this in its complete
state. There is no way that body would
have fitted originally into this coffin.
[music]
It seems seems to fit in to me. I mean,
it's in there.
>> Yeah. But you can see it here. I mean,
where the body's gone into the coffin,
particularly around the shoulder region,
it's taken off paint down the side of
the coffin where it's been squeezed in.
>> Egyptian mummies were generally very
well wrapped. We've got documented
evidence of, you know, up to 250 square
meters of linen wrappings being used on
these individuals.
The mummy's size is a clear sign that
something's not right, but the team is
going to need more to go on to have a
chance of cracking the case.
>> There's a distinct facial feature there
of uh overjet.
>> Oh, what?
>> It's almost like book teeth.
>> All right.
>> Um in which you have the upper set of
teeth protruding very much over the
bottom set. Now, this is potentially
quite an intriguing find because we know
from the evidence that's already been
collected that the royals, the royal
mummies, the pharaohs of the New Kingdom
also shared this distinct characteristic
for the ancient Egyptians. Everything
connected with death was significant. If
the team's going to find out who she was
and how she died, they can't afford to
leave any stone unturned.
One tiny mark on the mummy's face could
be the key to the story.
>> I think for me it's the um the puck
marking on the skin. U whether this is
um embarmming to do with the
mummification or or whether it's
something else or just bad skin. Well,
hasn't it been suggested that the mummy
of Ramsy's the 5th had smallox cuz he's
got these postures on his face?
>> That's true, but the science wasn't
particularly convincing.
>> The next step in the investigation will
be critical. The 3,000-year-old mummy is
priceless and incredibly delicate. If
the team put a foot wrong while they're
gathering evidence, they could [music]
destroy the very clues they're looking
for.
Any
human contact could contaminate the
chemical evidence. So, Steven Buckley
takes his samples first.
Every substance has its unique chemical
fingerprint.
Steven's analysis of imbalming materials
can yield clues about ancient trade
routes, religious strife, and even the
politics of ancient Egypt.
The combinations of ingredients used for
imbalming vary enormously over the
thousands of years of Egyptian history.
And identifying the chemical mix in a
particular case can help pinpoint a
date.
If Steven can identify the individual
chemicals present in these samples,
[music]
the specific combinations could have a
symbolic significance that will tell us
about the mummy's [music] life and
death.
The chemical analysis will take days, if
not weeks, to process.
The next move is down to Dr. Fletcher.
She calls in [music] some specialist
help to examine the pictograms that
cover the side of the coffin.
Could hieroglyphics expert Alan Files
reveal vital information for the team?
>> So, Alan, what do you make of these
particular hieroglyphs?
>> 21st Dynasty. Yeah,
>> you can tell by the yellow and the the
orange. Um, we have Neb Purr again, lady
of house, a chantress of Ammonra.
>> So, who sung before the gods and played
instruments for the gods in the temple,
a very high stage
>> presumably at Carac
temple. She'd be sort of a regular
performer before the gods.
>> There's an interesting story here, isn't
there?
>> Nearly every [music] detail of the
mummy's life is apparently recorded on
the coffin. She was a singer, probably
at one of Egypt's greatest temples,
Carac, participating in rituals with a
sacred rattle [music] called a cyrum.
It's a great start for the
investigation.
>> We've certainly got plenty of clues to
go on. Absolutely.
>> All the elements are there. We've just
got to put them together and and try and
make sense [music] of it all.
>> Another mystery upon us, but a lovely
piece of work.
The title written on the coffin,
Chantress of Amoon, was just as much a
badge of social prominence as a job
description. Chantresses would be
highclass women who would spend one
month in three assisting at temple
ceremonies.
In ancient Egypt, the temples were
highly restricted and jobs that provided
access to them were reserved for the
elite of Egyptian society.
The hieroglyphs have given Joanne a
wealth of information about the mummy,
but shed no light on the cause of death.
In search of a breakthrough, Joanne has
brought in some heavyweight help.
Paleopathologist Professor Don
Brothewell has an international
reputation [music] that extends far
beyond the world of archaeology. His
investigations of everything from mass
murders to Danish bog bodies have made
him a world authority. With the help of
a full body X-ray scan, Don will be able
to see beneath the mummy's ancient skin
[music] and the wrappings that cover her
lower body to identify any injuries that
could relate to her cause of death.
And here the bottom of the spine is
seen.
And there seems to be some material
inside the abdomen here, doesn't there?
What exactly might be revealed later on?
The upper teeth are very um projected in
front of the lower teeth. So you have a
rather sort of prominent upper teeth in
the jaw.
And the wear on the teeth suggests to me
that's not particularly marked.
>> The fact that Don's dental inspection
has revealed very little wear on the
teeth means the mummy must have enjoyed
a high status diet of soft food and been
less than 30 years old at the time of
her death. This young woman was struck
down in the prime of her life.
We have something at the back of the
skull which looks as if we have a
deposit
at the back either something pushed into
the skull through the nasal area through
the nose. Right. Can we move on to the
thigh? Not a particularly large head of
the feur, which
isn't a very masculine um feature, but
combined with the pelvic detail, I would
say this is a fairly slenderly built
male.
>> This bombshell that the mummy is
actually male means the team will have
to rethink all their assumptions.
>> Steve, interesting results. We've done
these digital x-rays
and um what we find in the skull and in
the pelvis is very definite evidence
that this is a male
>> ah
>> not female
>> right
>> there's enough information from the the
detail of the skull things like the
frontal sinuses and parts of the pelvis
which indicates you know the sex of the
individual
>> I'm absolutely sure this is male
>> right so interesting puzzle
>> don 's search for the mummy's cause of
[music] death has totally transformed
its identity.
The fact that it's male, not female,
helps explain why it doesn't fit in the
coffin. But if this isn't the coffin's
original occupant, all of the
information from the casket's
inscriptions is irrelevant. The
investigation is almost back to square
one.
The team needs a fresh start.
Egyptologist Jill Scott wants to find
out if modern dental medicine can tell
us anything about the mummy. [music]
So, she tracks down orthodontic
consultant Jay Kinderellan.
>> Well, the mummy demonstrates a
combination of both [music] prominence
of the upper front teeth uh and also an
element of what we would call mandibular
retrusion. So, the lower jaw is actually
set back in relation to the rest of the
face.
>> The unusual combination of these two
facial deformities would have made life
difficult. I think the main issue would
have been one of uh eating food. Um the
mummy may not have been able to bite
into an apple normally or if they had
sandwiches in Egyptian times, they may
not have been able to bite a sandwich
properly. Um the mummy probably would
have had to chop up the food to put in
separately.
>> And what about speaking?
>> Absolutely. I mean there are many sounds
including closive sounds where you would
put your lips together to make the
necessary noise. um our mommy really
wouldn't have been able to function in
that way. Uh and lisping would have been
a real problem.
>> A picture is emerging of an individual
beset by problems. A young man with
trouble eating, speaking, everyday
things that we take for granted.
But while his distinctive teeth were
troublesome, could his condition also be
a sign that he wasn't as unlucky as he's
beginning to appear?
A family album of ancient Egyptian
pharaohs hints at a possible royal
connection. [music]
>> And there is the supposition here that
these people were all related.
>> So it tends to run in families. So the
mummy's parents [music] probably would
have had a similar facial profile. Um
and it would be passed down from one
generation to the next. We have patients
referred to maybe 11, 12, 13 years of
age. and and often as their parents walk
through the door with patients, you can
see really how the children are going to
turn out in later life,
>> right? Without without treatment
obviously.
>> Absolutely. I mean, it is very possible
that uh the mummy and these other
individuals have come from the same
genetic stock if you like. Uh but those
features alone wouldn't really point you
to the fact they were definitely
related. Uh what you really need to do
is get into something like
three-dimensional facial reconstruction.
So you can see [music] what the face is
like in all planes of space.
>> The dental evidence suggests the mummy
could be related to royalty, but it's
going to take facial reconstruction and
further investigations to confirm that.
A picture of the mummy is building up,
[music] but the team's no closer to
discovering how he died. Joanne calls a
meeting. With his textbook knowledge of
ancient diseases, Professor [music] Don
Brothewell could help pin down the
mummy's cause of death.
>> What do you think about this sort of
[music]
marking on the face? It's quite a
suspicious looking thing, doesn't it?
>> I mean, it does look like a rash,
doesn't it? [music]
>> Well, that's interesting because quite a
few Egyptologists when they see these
features on mummies have sort of raised
the question, is it smallox? Is it
evidence for some sort of sort of killer
disease? Small pox was a massive killer
in the ancient world, responsible for
millions of deaths worldwide.
Victims of smallox are covered with
pestules that break off to leave ugly
scarring resembling the marks on the
mummy's face. With no known cure, a
diagnosis of small pox was a death
sentence until the disease was almost
eradicated by vaccination in the last
100 years.
Dawn's vast knowledge of human remains
enables him to make a quick judgment.
>> My guess is it's postmortem. It extends
on to only regions of the of the body.
Uh and I've seen the same kind of thing
in bog bodies, for instance. And and
again, I think it's postmortem.
>> The most likely explanation for the
marks on the mummy's face is drying out
of the skin during the imbalming
process.
With the killer disease eliminated as a
cause of death, the team turns to
in-depth [music] analysis of the X-ray
results for answers.
>> The brain box is obviously empty except
[music] for what looks like a deposit at
the back of the head. And all those
little fragments there due to the damage
when the po whatever metal implement it
was was driven in. Think that explains
this sort of area of is it bone, is it
loose bone? Because I was interested in
cross referencing with the sort of
X-rays of Toot and K, the most famous
ancient Egyptian of them all. But you
also have what appears to be a kind of
bone fragment which for for many years
was regarded as a cause of death. You
know, this bash on the head was King Tut
murdered and all that.
>> So I'm interested on your thoughts on
that little tiny fragment there.
Bone fragments in the brain cavity could
be evidence of foul play. Are they signs
of a blow to the head like the one
thought by many to have killed King
Tuten Carmon? Or are they just a
byproduct of the mummification process?
>> So Adam, do you think to try and work
out exactly what's going on on this
X-ray image, we ought to undertake some
form of experiment?
>> Yeah, I think it'd be well worthwhile.
Um, as long as you don't call me in.
>> A lot of force is going to be needed,
isn't it?
>> It is. Yes. Uh, so
Can we just have a word about this?
>> I'm not entirely happy with the way this
is going judging by the conversation
that we've been having.
>> Well, I think we need somebody with a
fair amount of of strength on this one.
It's trying to recreate what we're
seeing on the X-ray here. We know that
the brain was removed by some sort of
force up through the nose with a metal
tool and then the brain was taken out.
>> So, what we're trying to do is recreate
the sort of damage that you're getting
within this the human skull in an
experimental way. Well, let's wait and
see what happens because I'm far from
convinced that's going to be an easy job
for you.
>> If the experiment can produce chips of
bone in the skull, it could be a major
step in the investigation. But
replicating a 3,000-year-old brain
removal process will be easier said than
done.
The removal of the brain was just one
stage of mummification.
For an ancient Egyptian, the
preservation of their body after death
was the key to eternal life. So,
tremendous importance was attached to
every aspect of the imbalming process.
To prevent decay, the main internal
organs other than the heart and kidneys
were removed and stored separately.
Removing the organs without damaging the
rest of the body required tremendous
skill on the part of the imbalmer.
With the experiment underway to try to
explain the bone fragments inside the
skull, the investigation is making
headway. And at the team's
state-of-the-art chemical laboratory,
Steven [music] Buckley could be one step
closer to finding the mummy's identity.
After hours of careful preparation, the
first results from [music] Steven's
chemical analysis are starting to come
through.
GCMS is the gold standard when it comes
to identifying organic [music]
chemicals. It provides a graphic
fingerprint of every chemical compound
within a minute sample. That can mean
hundreds of substances in a sample the
size of a pin head.
>> What GCMS allows us to do is to identify
components individually from a very
complex mixture. There's plenty of
components in there. So hopefully some
of them will be quite interesting.
From what we know so far, certain
substances were associated with
particular with certain deities. So
there's certainly symbolism, certainly
symbolism as well as the practical uh
materials. There's no question about
that.
I suppose we're really looking for the
more minor components
that may tell us something about
political identity,
religious affiliations, trade routes,
that sort of thing.
The GCMS machine heats the tiny samples
[music] until they turn into gas. The
temperature at which substances in the
samples vaporize plays a key part in
identifying them. Hours later, he has
his first breakthrough.
>> This is a major component in the sample
uh thymol. It's actually a lot of it in
time. for example.
What it certainly points out already um
to me is um that the inbalmers knew
their stuff that they were choosing
materials that would have genuinely have
preservative properties, antibacterials.
So thyol is is quite a powerful
antibacterial.
>> Identifying 3,000y old plant [music]
residues would be impressive enough, but
not for Steven Butley. He can even tell
you what altitude they grew at. What we
certainly have is a conifer resin. What
I'm trying to look for now are markers
that suggest um a mountain a mountain
conifer.
If conifers are exposed to uh higher
levels of radiation as they are at
higher altitude, then they actually give
um a chemical fingerprint showing that
and that that can sometimes give us
clues. The cocktail of expensive
imbalming ingredients containing a resin
from [music] a distant mountain conifer
confirms the team's thoughts that the
mummy must have been someone very
important. It also hints [music] at
exactly who this mummy may have been,
but that can only emerge after days of
painstaking analysis.
While Steven's making progress on the
mummy's identity on his own, Joanne's
going to need some help to carry out her
experiment on the cause of the mummy's
skull damage. [music]
The fundamentals of metal working
haven't changed for thousands of years.
Don Barker is still practicing skills
that would be familiar to any ancient
medical tool maker. Egyptian imbalming
tools were originally made in copper, a
soft metal easily bent into shape, but
almost as easily broken. Copper was
eventually replaced by stronger metals.
So, they're using authentic ancient
designs to make tools in both copper and
iron to see if either can produce the
kind of bone chips seen in the mummy.
>> Wow, that's amazing. You can really get
a feel for how they might have done it.
Now you know
>> for the whisking process to liquefy the
brain for removal. Joanne has another
tool made a long thin wire that will
curve around the inside of [music] the
skull.
>> So yeah, you can see how you could feed
it.
>> Yeah.
>> Up the nose.
>> And then once it's up, [music] then it's
like a handle to rotate.
>> Absolutely.
>> With the replica ancient Egyptian tools
complete, [music] everything is set for
a hands-on practical experiment which
could determine whether these kinds of
implements could have been the cause of
the mummy's skull damage.
Following the revelation that our mummy
is male, Duncan meets facial [music]
reconstruction specialist Stephanie Davy
Jouo to build a picture of what he may
actually have looked like.
>> So, I have a virtual model of the skull
here.
>> Okay.
>> And what I then do is an analysis of the
skull to determine um sex uh approximate
age
>> as well as ethnic affiliation. if I can
determine that.
>> With these parameters in place,
Stephanie uses data gathered from modern
populations to make an estimate of skin
depth that she then applies to the
model.
>> I can add
eyes.
Um, every person has approximately the
same size of eyes, but the placement
inside of the eye socket or the orbital
um is dependent upon the individual. One
thing that was interesting that I
noticed when reconstructing this
individual was the market asymmetry in
his orbitals. His eyes aren't even.
>> Like the deformed jaw, the asymmetric
eyes are another characteristic of some
18th and 19th dynasty Egyptian royalty.
[music] As the pieces come together, the
mummy's looks seem to become more and
more extraordinary.
>> And you'll notice too in profile [music]
you can see he's got quite a receding
chin.
>> Mhm. um coupled with the overjet and
he's got [music] a a convex nose. So,
he's got kind of a beaky nose and a
receding chin.
>> You're not building up a very good
picture of what this gu is going to look
like.
>> I build it as I
>> distinctive. Distinctive,
[clears throat]
but yeah, can't hide from [music] the
facts.
>> As the dental evidence suggests, the
mummy was a young man with a whole host
of problems. [music] And next I can
begin to build this the overlaying skin
surface using the information from the
tissue depths and the muscles and the
shape of the skull. And you can begin to
see what [music] he looked like.
>> It's incredible as well.
>> And then
>> he's certainly um choose my words
carefully. Distinctive, isn't it?
>> It is. Yes. I don't think [music] he'd
make any modern magazine covers.
>> No.
With a forensically accurate picture of
the [music] mummy, the investigation
gains new impetus. The team are no
longer dealing with desiccated remains,
but a human being whose cause [music] of
death remains unknown.
Duncan and Joanne are poised to conduct
the experiment that should help decide
whether the mummy was killed by a blow
to the head or whether the bone chips in
the skull are the product of imbalming.
With human volunteers in short supply,
the team have to compromise.
>> In our case, uh we have to use a sheep's
head. But in many ways, the sheep and
the human in terms of size, the size of
the brain, etc. They are quite similar,
aren't they?
>> The ancient Egyptians believed the heart
was the center for thought and emotion.
So they were unscentimental about
removing the brain to stave off the
decomposition process. [music] But with
this, the idea was that it was forced up
inside the nose, broke the top of the uh
nasal bone, and then the brain inside
kind of whisked
uh liquefied in effect uh and then it
could be drained out back down the nose.
>> So, time for a tap.
>> Absolutely.
>> Horribly easy.
Just a few minutes into the experiment,
the team suffer a setback.
>> Now look, it's bending.
>> And that's exactly what the blacksmith
said would happen.
>> If we mark how far it's gone up, that
must have gone through into the cavity.
And it's bent around.
>> With the copper tool out of action,
Duncan is going to have to use a more
modern iron version to stand any chance
of recreating the damage in the mummy's
skull.
It's much much tougher and uh and hasn't
bent around the skull cavity, but has
definitely gone through it. In fact, I'm
probably not going to be able to take
this out again now.
>> Hence the damage to the
>> No, that's lovely. Look at that.
>> And these are fantastic because this is
exactly I wouldn't be able to extract
all of these with the hook. I don't
think I could pull all of the brain out.
>> Chunks of brain tissue are a good start,
but bone fragments remain elusive.
Egyptian imbalmer could remove a brain
by liquidizing it in as little as 20
minutes. If Duncan can't produce bone
chips in this time with the more
destructive iron tool, the test must be
considered a failure.
>> So, the 20 minutes is up, Duncan. So,
uh, how's it gone?
>> Look, I can't actually quite believe I'm
saying this, but it's been incredibly
interesting. I mean what I've been able
to do is extract actually quite a lot of
the brain tissue here using um both this
the smaller and thinner whippier action
but also with the heavy duty tool as
well. um material has been coming out,
but what's interesting me most of all is
that within this material there are
chips of bone. Really very clear shards
of bone.
>> That's exactly what we were seeing on
the x-rays of the bolt mummy.
>> I'll just take the skull and tip it up
here and see whether we get anything
coming out through the nasal cavity.
I have spent a long, you know, it's good
20 minutes and violently moving the
instruments around, but what we get is a
big fat zero. Absolutely nothing. The
brain may not have completely liquidized
in 20 minutes, but the experiment is
still a major boost for the
investigation. The brain removal process
has produced visible chips of bone.
With the embalming procedure itself
clearly capable of causing this damage,
there's just no reason to suppose that
our mummy was hit on the head. It must
be ruled out of the investigation.
With one cause of death eliminated, the
team are making real progress. Now, some
hard work in the lab is uncovering
exciting developments in the quest for
the mummy's identity. Remnants of cloth
from the mummy's wrappings contain
[music] telltale evidence. Certainly one
of the things that struck me
particularly when I was looking at the
actual mummy in Bolton, the very sort of
fine quality of this linen [music]
because quite a lot of mummies, Egyptian
mummies certainly are wrapped in
[clears throat] quite often quite coarse
material often reused, [music]
recycled even amongst sort of what you
call the middle classes I guess but with
this one it's it's really fine stuff
[music] you know the finest quality
>> definitely
>> and it's almost as if the linen's being
applied a little bit like [music] papia
mâe. It's been applied in a thin layer
and then coated in something and then
another layer of wrapping applied and
another layer of coating. So, I'd really
be interested [music] to see if the
coatings applied on each layer and
certainly at different areas of the
body. There's plenty to sort of [music]
go on here, isn't there? There's a lot
of interesting things at play. I think
>> Joannne's examination of the fabric
confirms the team's [music] first
instincts that the mummy is someone very
high class, but the results of Steve's
chemical analysis promise dramatic new
developments.
>> The chemistry is looking is actually
looking quite interesting. We've got a
lot of thymol um which is something that
occurs in in time for example. What
we've also got with this triuroid resin
is pistachio. Well, that's a very
distinctive chemical fingerprint. All
those ingredients put together.
>> To some extent, it's a royal marker. So,
I think it suggests this was was someone
of note um given the the amount that's
being used.
>> The pistachio shrub, prized for its
sweet smelling resin, was used almost
exclusively for embarmming members of
Egyptian royalty during the era of the
New Kingdom.
Suddenly, the notion that our mummy is
of royal descent has gone from an
intriguing idea to a definite
possibility. But Steven has even more
surprises up his sleeve.
>> What's also in [music] interesting
curious initially was the fact we
actually have a a division. So a line is
being drawn through the mummy if you
like. The left side suggests sheep,
possibly goat. with the right side. He's
got [music] cow or bull.
>> One half of the mummy's upper body was
covered in sheep fat, the other in cow
fat. Each substance symbolically linked
[music] to rival Egyptian gods.
>> Sheep or goat of the sacred ram of a
moon represented the sort of grand
traditions of of the ancient Egyptians.
But then he's sort of playing [music]
both sides, isn't he? is sort of
>> exactly
>> showing evidence of of of the sort of
cow sort of bovine material. He's got
this linked to [music]
Hatheror, the boine goddess linked to
the sun.
>> It's an incredible discovery by
analyzing tiny drops of fat taken from
both sides of the body. Steven Buckley
has opened up a dramatic chapter of
Egyptian history.
Egypt in 1250 BC [music] was politically
divided between north and south.
Hatheror the cow was daughter of the
ancient sun god Rah, a symbol of the
north, favored by priests who were loyal
to the pharaoh. The god Ammoon
represented by a ram was the chief deity
of the powerful priests [music] who
dominated the south.
I think the chemistry is telling us that
this person is is playing a very careful
uh political and religious game. Um he
wants to get the balance right. He's
actually um showing that he's pro moon
and um pro ra.
>> When you think there's all this
political upheaval going on in ancient
Egypt and it's encapsulated in a a tiny
sample the size of a pin head.
>> If the mummy was performing [music] this
delicate political and religious
balancing act in death, it narrows down
the possibilities of who they were in
life. So on the basis of [music] this
amazing data, are we able to sort of try
and pinpoint more precisely who this
this person may or may not be? I
>> I think for me from from the chemistry
[music] and the mummification evidence
that we have, it suggests a possible
Ramise II connection
>> with the shaven [music] head. That's an
interesting one because of course it's a
clear mark of a priest. In isolation,
the mummy's lack of hair wouldn't be
significant, but combined with all the
other evidence of [music] his status,
his distinctive facial features, and the
religious importance of his imbalming
materials, it's [music] a key indicator
of his identity.
>> Then potentially, we're looking at one
of the royal sons of one of the
pharaohs.
The chemistry suggests [music]
this mummy was rich and important. A
prince of the royal house, a priest, and
a political player in one of the most
turbulent periods in Egyptian history.
The incredible 66-year reign of Rammeses
II was an exciting time to be alive in
ancient Egypt. Led by its extravagant
king, the Egyptian Empire expanded
dramatically before slowly tumbling into
economic decline. Rammeses was
responsible for building some of the
most spectacular monuments in ancient
Egypt, many of which survive today. The
temple complexes at Carne and the
Ramiseum forever pay silent tribute to
an era of great achievements and great
political intrigue.
The teeth, the eyes, the chemistry, and
the shaven head all point to one
identity.
Of the hundreds of children that
Rammeses II fathered, many would be sent
into the priesthood, where they could
enjoy some of the most powerful and
privileged positions in Egyptian
society.
From within their magnificent temples,
the priesthood could exert control over
every aspect of Egyptian life.
>> [music]
>> The team are managing to put together an
extraordinary picture of who this mummy
was in life, but they're no closer to
knowing how he died. For an answer to
this vital question, [music] they'll
need some high techch assistance.
A CAT scan, computerass assisted
tomography, uses a series of X-rays to
build a 3D image of the body.
Hundreds of images [music] taken from
360°
around the body are combined to build
the picture.
With this state-of-the-art imaging
device, paleopathologist Don Brothewell
can find traces [music] of injury or
illness in the ancient mummy that would
elude a normal X-ray.
>> What we're hoping to find here is any
evidence of abnormality. So, we ought
really to look particularly to see
whether we can find any incision. If
they find an oblique imbalming incision,
it'll place the mummy in Egypt's 18th
[music] dynasty, and everything the team
has discovered would be thrown into
question again.
If the incision is vertical, the mummy
would be tied to the 19th dynasty,
[music] the time of Rammeses II.
>> Is that a cut in
>> that area? I'm just trying to compare it
to the other side.
>> During imbalming, [music] the organs
would be removed through a single cut in
the abdomen. After mummification, it
would generally [music] be tightly
stitched, making the incision very thin
and hard to find.
>> It's the left hand side where we should
be finding the incision, right?
Remember, it's it would be stitched up.
>> The skill of the Egyptian imbalmer makes
it a difficult search, but eventually
they find it. It's a vertical incision.
The discovery of the incision puts the
mummy squarely in the time of Rammeses
II, but further [music] investigation
will be needed to identify how the mummy
died.
>> But obviously, if we really are going to
try and find the cause of death, we need
to work over every image very carefully.
Back in York, detailed analysis of the
CT scans has uncovered a surprise hidden
beneath the mummy's wrappings.
>> Aha,
this is a man.
>> So, we're coming down now into the
pelvis.
Can you see [music] we're beginning to
get a separate structure showing up
there beyond the abdomen? I'm fairly
sure we're seeing sections of the penis
there. So, this man, all right,
>> that looks very very sort [music] of
dense.
>> It looks like it's been quite well
wrapped.
>> Well, it's been well prepared for death
and the next life, I suppose. But what
puzzles me is I can't see any evidence
of a scrotum or testicles.
The imbalmeras have taken great care to
leave the mummy well prepared for the
afterlife, [music] but their
preparations have left us with a puzzle.
>> We're dealing with a sort of section
through the arm about here. Look how
tight the skin is. Again, we seem to be
dealing with a body with not very much
tissue around the bone.
>> It does look very high status, a member
of the elite, and you'd imagine had a a
very very uh high status diet. If there
is this evidence of sort of potential
emaciation, does that suggest this
individual was undernourished?
>> Or it could be a disease, couldn't it?
Or the alternative is a cancer. So could
it be that that's causing this?
>> Cancer can cause dramatic weight loss
irrespective of diet. Just like today,
it was a problem for the ancient
Egyptians. Even for young men in the
prime of life like the mummy,
>> there's no good evidence of growths or
erosions into tissue which suggest to me
that it is, you know, that you've got
secondary cancers.
>> So no tumors are running,
>> no tumor evidence there at all except
for the thinness of the body. We might
of course um be dealing with a body
where the actual tumorous tissue has
been removed by the umbrellas. Yeah,
it's quite possible given how skilled it
were.
>> Yeah, that's right.
>> While the mummy's body shows signs of
cancer, the cancerous tissue itself,
like the mummy's scrotum, is
mysteriously absent. Could these two
absences be linked?
Today, testicular cancer is relatively
rare, but it can still be deadly.
3,000 years ago, it was even deadlier.
The problem might be diagnosed, but was
impossible to treat.
When a cancer sufferer died, the
imbalmeras were known to remove ugly
cancerous growths so that their bodies
were again perfect for the afterlife.
The mummies of Rammeses II and his son
Manpa both had their testicles removed.
Whether this is evidence of a hereditary
vulnerability to cancer or simply a
family mummification tradition is hard
to say. But crucially, the scans have
raised a real possibility for how the
mummy died.
At Bolton Museum, Don Brothewell joins
Steven Buckley in trying an old
technique that could fill out the final
branch of the mummy's family tree.
Facial reconstruction has brought to
life the mummy's extraordinary features.
But to prove that they are a family
trait, another test is needed.
The facial features that determine a
person's looks can be scientifically
measured and compared with cranioacial
measurements of family members.
The proportions of the nose and chin can
be just as distinctive as fingerprints.
>> What I've seen is some interesting
patterns in in the royal mummies. Yeah.
>> And there's some hints at at possible
similarities here. So it's a question of
you know what we can get out of that by
doing getting accurate measurements
here.
>> Accuracy in these measurements is
absolutely essential. The tiniest
mistake [music] could render the results
meaningless.
>> Upper facial height would be nice.
>> That's a problem, isn't it?
>> That's right. The lip [music]
is obscuring the uh
>> get and preventing us getting an
accurate measurement. So I think perhaps
the X-ray the X-rays might provide a
>> I mean an accurate measurement there. I
think
>> Yeah.
Cranioacial measurements can [music] be
taken from a human body or from X-rays.
It's an old technique dating back to the
19th century. Nowadays, it's rarely used
[music] in modern criminal
investigations where DNA has become the
single most important tool in positively
identifying individuals. But DNA is
vulnerable to extremes of temperature
and is almost certain to have been
destroyed by heat, time, and the
substances used in imbalming. [music]
For ancient artifacts like Egyptian
mummies, cranioacial measurement will
always stand the test of [music] time.
Back in York, the final piece of the
jigsaw is almost in place.
However accurate Steven's measurements
are, they mean nothing on their own.
To prove scientifically that this mummy
is related to Rammeses II, the
statistics must be compared with data
gathered from Egyptian royal mummies,
including Rammeses himself.
>> I looked at all the royal mummies that
we have from the new kingdom.
>> The one that stands out um as being most
similar to ours is Rammeses the second.
Of these six key measurements, four of
them are virtually identical
>> with Ramsey's a second.
>> Yes, with Ramsey second.
>> The link between these two mummies is
not just statistical. The resemblance is
more than skin deep.
>> Here's the X-ray of Rammeses the second.
>> That is so similar. Look at that.
>> Yeah.
>> Look at the nose. The degree of overjet,
the angle, the angle
>> and the chin. That is such a
distinction.
>> The jaw, the remite jaw.
>> The mummy differs significantly from
Rammeses II in only two measurements.
Surprisingly, these two rogue statistics
actually reinforce the mummy's link to
Rammeses through his father seti.
>> Other than these couple of measurements
here where it's seti the first, who as
we know was Ramsey the second's father.
Yeah. So that's that will be expected
from father to son and then our
individual.
>> That's amazing.
>> That's quite good, isn't it?
>> Yeah.
>> The mystery of the mummy's identity
appears to be solved at last. [music]
He's almost certainly a blood relative
of one of Egypt's greatest pharaohs.
>> What we find in the skull and in the
pelvis is very definite evidence [music]
that this is a male. I mean it is very
possible that uh the mummy and these
[music] other individuals have come from
the same genetic stock if you like.
>> I think the chemistry is telling us that
this person is is playing a very careful
uh political and religious game.
>> That is so similar. Look at that.
>> Well, it could be a disease, couldn't
it? Or the alternative is a cancer.
>> After weeks of intense work, the
investigation has yielded discoveries
[music] no one could have anticipated.
to come to the point we have as in a
relative of Ram Caesar the second is is
quite mind-blowing that
>> any one of those [music] pieces of
information if we hadn't had it if we
hadn't found it could have taken us in a
completely different direction
>> for maybe we just let the science do
[music] the talking
>> um it speaks for itself
>> for this mummy the science speaks
volumes contrary to the inscriptions on
[music] the casket this mummy is male
switched into the casket either in Egypt
or during his long journey to Britain
and Bolton Museum
The team's painstaking work has painted
a picture of a fascinating life and
suggested that the mummy could have died
of cancer while still young.
>> So, so basically [music] this person had
a life of wanting for absolutely nothing
which which makes, you know, the manner
of his death such an irony, [music]
doesn't it?
>> As Don flagged up, it certainly appears
to be some sort of wasting disease,
possibly even cancer. I mean, that's
that's a tragic irony.
This rich, powerful man who should have
enjoyed a comfortable existence at the
pinnacle of Egyptian society was perhaps
humbled by a condition that respects
neither wealth nor power and still
haunts us today.
Every time we we look at the the
mummies, look at the bodies, it's it's
not um you know an object in [music]
space and time. It's it's not um I don't
understand them because this is a status
individual. You you connect on a very
human way. We aren't looking at just
[music] some artifact in a museum. This
is a living, breathing human being that
people once loved and once cared for.
>> They had [music] the same fears that we
did and the same felt the same pain that
we did.
>> I think that's why it's nice that um
we've gone some way to giving him his
identity back.
>> The idea of gaining immortality through
mummification might seem strange to us,
but in a very real sense, this mummy's
imbalmer succeeded in their task. Their
careful work has ensured that his memory
and his identity will endure for
thousands of years beyond his death.
[music]
>> Somebody here wants this lady to suffer
for the rest of eternity.
We may have a crime here, but we've got
no body.
>> Certainly a puzzle. uh and possibly
suggest something a little sinister.
>> There's so many suspicious [music]
elements to this story. It's really
giving me cause for concern.
>> It would just be a world of pain.
[music]
Yeah.
Mummification, [music]
the preservation of dead bodies, became
more than a science in ancient Egypt.
It developed into a sacred ritual.
No other people in history devoted so
much time and expense to ensuring a safe
passage into the eternal afterlife with
their body intact.
The skill of Egypt's master inbalmers
was phenomenal. Thousands of years ago,
they worked to halt the ravages of time
on lifeless corpses. [music]
Today, forensic technology can unlock
that person's secrets to reveal [music]
the intimate story of their life and
death.
Over 2,000 [music] mi from Egypt in a
museum in the north of England lies the
beautifully preserved coffin of an
Egyptian mummy.
But the body inside [music] remains a
mystery.
The workmanship and sophistication of
this coffin suggest that it would have
taken weeks, if not months, to create.
To be worthy of this topof the- range
casket, its owner must surely have been
a VIP.
Dr. Joanne Fletcher is a renowned
Egyptologist [music]
who's done excavation work and mummy
investigations around the world.
She's been called in to try and unlock
the secrets [music] of this hidden
mummy.
>> It came into this country a couple
hundred years ago and rather than going
to [music] the British Museum or another
major institution, it came up here to
Newcastle.
>> Well, it's obviously [music] an Egyptian
mummy covering. It's obviously female
from the from the exterior at least. So,
I'd be quite interested [music] to sort
of try and find out more about this
individual inside. So, I'm really
looking forward to sort of seeing the
mummy.
>> Um, I'm afraid we can't do that. We
really can't open this up [music] um cuz
we're worried about damaging this
beautiful object.
>> So, is she completely sealed? [music]
>> Yes, she is.
>> There's no small openings that we could
take any samples or anything. No,
>> it's completely completely sealed. Yeah.
>> Um, yes. This is going to be quite a
challenge, I think.
First and foremost, what I'd really like
to do [music] is take a series of
photographs uh from every angle pretty
much so I can then go back to talk with
the team in York and try and plan some
sort of strategy, see what techniques we
can bring to bear to study this uh this
very enigmatic and fascinating mummy.
>> [music]
>> This sealed coffin may be an exquisite
work of art, but it's also an ancient
mystery thousands of years in the
making.
Joanne's already nicknamed the hidden
mummy the lady.
And piece by piece, she and the team
will have to fill in all the details of
who she was, where she's from, and how
she met her end.
This case will be a [music] massive
challenge for the mummy investigation
team given the coffin is sealed and they
will never be able to see or touch the
mummy within.
The team are among the best in their
field, but even for them, the task would
probably be impossible, except for one
thing.
2 years ago, for conservation purposes,
the museum had the mummy [music]
CT scanned.
Computed axial tomography is an advanced
form of the conventional X-ray.
Instead of revealing [music] the outline
of bones and organs, the CT scan forms a
full three-dimensional computer model of
the human body.
This medical blueprint of the lady will
allow the team to analyze specific areas
of the body [music] in great detail.
The forensic data will be a priceless
tool for the team as they try to uncover
how this woman lived and how she died.
Dr. Steven Buckley has an international
reputation for his [music] chemical
analysis of mummified bodies. His unique
experience may unlock a [music] vital
clue on this mysterious coffin. Well,
from the chemistry, it's certainly
possible that some [music] sort of
concealment was going on.
>> Egyptologist Jill Scott specialist
knowledge in ancient human remains
[music] will be crucial in unraveling
the real story of how this mummy died.
>> Injuries like that I would expect to be
lowered down. It is very high up.
And Duncan Lees, [music] who offers
forensic support to criminal
investigations all over the UK, is going
to bring modern detective techniques to
the case of this Egyptian mummy. Just
cuz they're 3,000 years old doesn't mean
that we can't apply modern [music]
forensics and come up with good answers.
>> The lady, like every case, begins with a
team briefing here in the incident room
at the University of York.
Joanne begins with the bad news.
>> We aren't allowed to take this covering
off. We aren't allowed to do any
physical sampling with this. There is no
way into this, Mommy.
>> The team gets straight into analyzing
the CT scan data.
What interests me here is this um this
sort of package which I'm guessing is
part of the embalming process the
modification uh internal organs wrapped
in there. But there is a lot that we can
do. I mean, using technology that that
that Steven will be applying as well.
Um, that looks through the coffin, looks
into the interior and builds up still
three-dimensional information that will
be a good starting point for us to
create a virtual reality person.
>> The whole premise with this one is it's
a completely, you know, hands-off zone.
We're not allowed to touch, but using
this technology to penetrate through the
wrappings, through the coffin, we can
hopefully then, you know, really bring
this woman back to life.
The team [music] have state-of-the-art
forensic technology like a CT scan at
their disposal.
But if [music] they're going to unlock
the secrets of this sealed coffin,
they'll have to do so with absolutely no
access to the body within.
To get things started, [music] they're
going back to basics.
Jill Scott is hard at work.
She's already unearthed the museum's
acquisition records and has discovered
that back in the 1820s, when the coffin
of this mummy first came into the
country, [music] it was opened at the
base by the feet.
The damage that was done during this
operation is one reason why the museum
insists the coffin must now remain
sealed.
Further analysis of the records reveals
[music] details that will help them
build a profile of the mummy.
And what we appear [music] to have is a
mummy dating from the 21st 22nd dynasty.
So we're looking around 1070 to 900 BC
as is a sort of rough date there.
>> The records [music] state that the name
of this mummy is Bak Hornat which means
servant of Horus the strong which makes
sense as a name for an Egyptian female.
[music]
>> And what we also have is a location. We
have it mentioned here that she was
found [music] in a tomb at Gerner and
thieves which is a really interesting
place.
>> Set along both sides of the river Nile
near the modern city of Luxor lies the
ancient city of thieves.
It was for a while prominent as a royal
residence, the [music] capital city and
the religious heart of Egypt.
It contained the necropolis in the
valley of the kings [music] and
numerouserary temples such as the
Ramiseum built by Rammeses II.
But for all its architectural splendor,
thieves was at the center of a bitter
rivalry that had split ancient Egypt in
two. [music]
The south around thieves is entirely
controlled by the priests. So you've got
these elite [music] priest kings, these
powerful powerful dynasts that that
control the whole area. [music] So
whoever our lady was, she was very much
under the thumb of these priests both on
a a religious and I'd say a political
level. I think the thing that [music]
interests me most of all is this Mona
Lisa type smile to her. Really enigmatic
[music] and it kind of makes you wonder
what's actually going on underneath this
coffin lay. You know, what is she
hiding?
In order to find out more about the
lady, the team need to establish what
she looked like in life.
But with [music] her body sealed in a
coffin, this won't be easy.
[music]
They've brought in an expert in cranial
facial identification.
Steph Davy Jiao uses her expertise on
criminal investigations and
archaeological cases. [music]
Taking the data from the CT scan, her
computerized reconstruction model will
reveal this woman's face for the first
time in thousands [music] of years.
>> This is a virtual 3D model of her skull.
Rather than showing you how she would
have looked now, I can show you what she
would have looked like at the end of her
life.
Steph has identified a number of changes
to the woman's facial structure caused
by the process of mummification.
>> Her jaw had been rotated into an open
position.
>> Okay.
>> And her nasal bones had been broken
likely when they removed her brain.
>> Okay.
>> So, I [music] rotated the mandible back
into its natural position.
And [music] I've taken the nasal bones a
bit like pieces of a puzzle. I was able
to rotate them back into where they
would have been.
>> Using standard tissue depth markers,
Steph is able to accurately recreate the
thickness of the skin all over the
mummy's face.
>> The next stage of the process is to add
eyes. These are obviously [music] quite
important to the final appearance of the
face.
>> All the pieces are beginning to click
into place as the face of the mummy is
slowly building.
So, I've begun to add skin. Essentially,
I've built a grid using the tissue
depths and the muscles to build [music]
the outer features of the face.
>> Is this a generic sort of mesh that
you've attached to the head or or does
this built up as a sort of bespoke data
set for this individual?
>> I make it bespoke each time, especially
in in regions such as the eyes and the
lips. It's very personal to the skull
beneath.
With the face almost complete, Steph
starts to add the finishing touches.
>> Here's an image rendered of what she
looks like without hair.
>> Okay.
>> Quite statuesque, I think.
>> Incredible. Very well, beautiful and
[music] very striking as well. Very
strong um features.
To build an accurate picture of her
hairstyle, Steph has modeled it on the
painting of the lady's hair on the
outside of the coffin.
>> And there she is.
>> That is extraordinary.
>> This is how she would have appeared on
the day that she died.
>> The face of a 3,000-y old mummy.
The ability to accurately rebuild the
face of this Egyptian woman as it was
the day she died almost 3,000 years ago
is an astonishing achievement for the
mummy investigation team,
especially as they've managed to do it
without even opening the coffin.
Now that you've finished the
reconstruction and and spent so long
working on it, what clues are hidden
away in her face that you've managed to
draw out?
>> Well, you can see she was a quite
striking looking woman.
And you can see here she's got quite um
an extensive overbite
and based on her overbite, we can say
with some confidence that she was likely
of high status. This has been shown um
in various research outputs.
An overbite is the vertical overlapping
of the upper teeth over the lower teeth.
It's a classic facial feature of
Egyptian royalty.
A physical characteristic dating back to
the lineage of pharaohs like Tuten
Carmun in the 18th dynasty.
This important discovery backs up the
theory that the mummy was a high status
Egyptian female.
>> [music]
>> The mummy investigation team are among
the first people to lay eyes on the
lady's facial features in almost [music]
3 millennia.
Using museum records, the team has also
confirmed her position at the top of
Egyptian society, probably originating
from the city of thieves during the 21st
to 22nd dynasty.
But they are still no closer to working
out exactly who she was or how she died.
[music]
Joanne is hoping that the hieroglyphs on
the coffin could provide a vital lead.
[music]
This ancient writing system contains a
combination of symbols and alphabetic
elements. [music]
Hieroglyphs were an essential component
of mummification as all Egyptian coffins
had to correctly display the name of the
person inside to ensure a safe passage
into the afterlife. [music]
They were first deciphered in 1822 by
[music] French scholar Jean Francois
Champolon who realized that the Rosetta
Stone was inscribed with [music] the
same text in both Greek and hieroglyphs,
an event that gave birth to [music] the
science of Egyptology.
Alan Files specializes in [music]
deciphering this ancient Egyptian
writing, and his knowledge could unlock
the secrets of this sealed coffin. In
his analysis of the hieroglyphs, Alan
has noticed a series of anomalies.
Ever since she was brought to Britain,
[music] she's been known as Bakorn,
which means servant of Horus the Strong.
But that's not [music] what is actually
written on the coffin.
>> We've got bar ke. [music]
>> Yeah.
>> Then we've got a very hurried uh water
sign.
>> It is hurried, isn't it?
>> They've not done a zigzag like normal,
>> which I'm sure would have been as easy
as enough [music] to write a water sign
as it is to do that line. So we have
backet
[__] [music]
>> which translates as simply servant of
Horus.
Then I see knack bett or knacked.
[music]
>> The word knacked meaning strong is
separated from bakenh [__] by the
equivalent of a full stop. This means
the [music] name actually reads as
baktenh [__] full stop. Adding a knack
seems to be a mistake by whoever
transcribed it for the museum. For over
200 years, this mummy has been given the
wrong name. [music] Servant of Horus the
Strong instead of her true name, Servant
of Horus.
Remembering the names of the dead was
sacred to ancient Egyptians. They
probably valued the afterlife more than
any other culture in history. They
believed that death was simply a
temporary interruption and that eternal
life could be ensured by preservation of
the physical form through mummification.
The pharaohs in particular were so
obsessed with the afterlife that they
ordered the construction of vast and
complex [music] tombs to protect their
bodies for this journey into the next
world.
The 19th century mistransation of the
name is one thing, but the original
scribe also seems to have made a
mistake.
>> Everything else
>> is actually spot on. It's well done.
does work.
>> And then we come to the major part of
the inscription and suddenly we send the
wrong person.
>> So we can't say with any certainty the
name of this lady.
>> Exactly.
>> Which means she can't live again.
>> She can't.
>> The description of the lady's status, a
vital insignia for the afterlife
contains what must be a deliberate
error.
>> This woman is called Lord of the House.
Absolutely.
>> And she's a lady of the house. You're
not a man. She's a woman. So at the top
they've got the sex wrong, which is
pretty fundamental. maximum to hurt,
isn't it? It's the maximum kind of thing
you can do to this lady to affect her.
>> Yeah. It was totally misrepresenting
what she was in life.
>> A gut instinct would be that I that
somebody
didn't want this person to live in the
next world. That an error so obvious as
that um somebody wanted to do mischief.
A thing so crucial as a name, a thing
that was going to take you and get you
allow you into the next world, a thing
that you couldn't live without. No, it's
a major major error. Or has it been done
for a reason?
The deliberate misrepresentation of the
mummy's title has thrown the case wide
open, leading Joanne and Allan to
consider who would have wanted to
sabotage the lady's passage into the
afterlife.
>> Well, there are a number of suspects,
aren't they? So, if we list the
subjects, we can actually have a look at
them. There's the family.
>> Yeah.
>> There's the scribes. And there's the
priesthood.
Could have been any of the three.
Let's face it, what what percent of um
Egyptians could read and write in this
period? Two or 1%. So, a scribe could
get away with that.
>> Yes.
>> Without 98% of people even looking.
>> Who would know? Who would know what the
scribe had written? That begs the
question, what's [music] going on inside
this car tonight?
>> Absolutely.
Symbolic damage [music] was done to the
inscription on the lady's coffin. The
team now needs to establish whether any
physical harm was done to her body.
Since they will never see inside the
coffin, Duncan has decided to use the
images from the CT scan to create a
precise model of the mummy's head.
Facial reconstruction established what
this woman looked like while alive.
Now he wants to know what she looks like
today sealed inside her coffin.
3D design specialist David Moore will
take data from the CT scan to form a
replica model of the mummy's head.
Commonly known as rapid prototyping,
this state-of-the-art technique will
allow the team to turn the digital data
into a 3D physical reality. We have a
fundamental problem with this with this
ob with this body, David, in that we
can't actually see her. Um, we've got
this cat scan data, but we really need a
visualization. We need really need to
sort of look her in the eye if we're
going to solve the case.
>> Well, see, the problem we've got here is
3,000 year old mommy is a lot of those
tissues have sort of ab absorbed into
each other and become attached to the
skull and things like that. That's what
we're what we're really going to have to
do is push the boundaries of the
software slightly and try and really
pick out just the material that we want.
>> Three-dimensional printers build up the
specific design by printing thousands of
successive layers.
The model is then created by alternating
layers of glue and chalk powder. The 3D
[music] result is a dimensionally
accurate head based on the source data
from the CT [music] scan.
>> If you're observing a real mummy, you
have to be so delicate, you know,
contamination, all everything that goes
with that.
>> What you've got here is an exact
representation of what's lying within
the casket. [snorts] Yet, you don't have
to be delicate with it. You can slice it
in half, see what's inside. In a way,
you haven't actually got a body here.
You're looking at data. [music]
[snorts]
Continuing to build the profile of the
lady, Joanne Fletcher is trying to gain
clues from one of the oldest forms of
forensic ID that exists,
teeth.
Dr. [music] Ian Mloud is a leading
dental radiologist who specializes in
the analysis of Egyptian mummies.
One of the things we can see straight
away, she's got a full set of teeth,
including [music] importantly her wisdom
teeth, the third mers.
And in most people, the third mer erupts
in your mouth [music]
at around the age of about 18. And it
takes another sort of 3 years for the
roots [music] to completely form. So if
we look carefully, we can see these
roots are fully formed.
>> [music]
>> So automatically we can say this lady's
over the age of 21. But if we look at
this lady's teeth, you can see that this
[music] is the first mer. This erupts
around the age of six. The second mer
erupts around the age of 12. And as
we've said, the third mer [music] about
18. Once the teeth are in the mouth,
this start to wear. And in ancient
Egypt, in fact, they they probably wore
their teeth quite rapidly. And if we
look at the top of the teeth there, we
can see that's worn [music] quite a lot.
This is a little less worn. And this
one's worn, but not to a huge degree.
So, putting these sort of facts
together, in fact, it [music] gives us
an age of around 30 at death.
Life was hard for most people living in
ancient Egypt, and the average life
expectancy was low.
A woman in her mid4s would be considered
elderly.
So, the fact that the lady was around 30
years old when she died makes it
unlikely that she died of old age.
Meanwhile, the 3D visualization of the
mummy is almost ready.
Without even laying a finger on the
coffin, Duncan is about to see exactly
[music] what the lady's head looks like.
The model's fantastic, isn't it?
And this is onetoone scale data. So
you're not reduced or changed in any way
the dimensions. So
>> she has a very
>> delicate small head, doesn't she?
>> It's incredible to be looking into her
face. And I wonder who the last person
she was looking at was.
[music]
Thousands of years after her death, the
Mummy investigation team are [music]
trying to piece together how and why
this Egyptian woman died.
So far, they know her name, her date of
origin, and where she lived.
And even though she remains sealed in a
coffin, the team now has an
extraordinary image of what the lady
once looked like.
They're now reconvening to try to work
out their next step.
>> What we have [music] isn't just a a
confusion with the name. There's
certainly confusion with this woman's
job title, the job description. We've
got clear evidence of misspelling
because these [music] signs should read
Nebet pair, which means lady of the
house.
>> And quite categorically, [music] that's
not what it says. When you look
carefully, they've purposefully missed
out the feminine tea sign. So,
>> so they're basically calling her a him.
>> Exactly. Exactly. And this [music] is
categorically wrong and and that's
completely contradicting the ancient
Egyptian belief systems.
>> So, I've had we've had a good step
forward as well with the uh [music] with
the data from the the cloud mapping from
the point cloud data that we've derived
from the CT scan. And this is going to
be the only chance I think we get to
look at um her in real life. And
here she is.
Steven [music] is a world authority on
mummification techniques.
He immediately notices a glaring [music]
discrepancy.
What um concerns me and I notice is the
um the difference between the fine
decorated cartonage uh and the state of
the u of the face. You see the um the
sort of undulation here. [music] Um
>> it's almost like it's blistered or
something, isn't it?
>> Egyptian imbalmer highly sophisticated
chemists who [music] developed their art
over thousands of years.
A good imbalmer would have preserved
facial features to an incredibly [music]
high standard.
[music] But the 3D model has revealed
the opposite.
>> It's certainly not [music] what you
would expect of um a decent armor um at
this time. There is definitely an
inconsistency here [music] and I think I
think that's something that needs
looking at.
>> Where I would go now with this is is to
look at the body and to see whether you
see it there.
>> Sure.
>> [music]
>> The evidence for foul play is building
up.
[music]
The team now need to find a cause of
death for the lady.
[music]
Using a print out of the CT scan, Duncan
is consulting surgeon commander Mike
Edwards, who serves with the British
forces.
He's seen practically every kind of
injury to the human body.
Armed with the CT scan data, he may be
able to tell what has happened to the
lady's body.
After careful analysis, Mike is able to
answer the question that has remained
unknown for 3,000 years.
How this woman died.
If we look on the CT scan here, we can
see that there is a massive incision or
stab wound, whatever you want to call
it, it is major and it's not regular at
all. It's ragged and irregular and
extends very deeply.
[music]
>> We're not talking about the the
mummification wound, the embalmer's
incision here. No, we're not because
this is more likely to be the embalming
incision because it's in the left loin
and left hypochondrial region which is
very
>> and it's very neat.
>> Yeah.
>> The large wound identified is completely
separate from the standard imbalming
incision
which is also visible on the CT scan.
This presents the team with a dramatic
development.
I suspect the wound is here.
>> Okay.
>> And this uh extends if if a a knife were
placed through the abdomen,
>> it would have gone through this small
bowel here, large bowel here,
[clears throat]
>> maybe even into the liver here and the
large vessels at the back of the
abdomen.
>> Why do we think this is a wound from a
stabbing rather than say damage from
impaling yourself or falling on
something, you know, that sort of thing?
>> Well, I think I think I'll go further
than that. I think this is an
assassination. I think the sight of the
wound tells us and the size of the
wound.
>> If we're imagining that I'm attacking
you from the front and if I'm coming in,
I'm trying to stab you here, your hands
are going to be all over the place. I'm
going to be trying stabbing you here,
here, and here.
>> And certainly not up and under.
>> Certainly not up and under. And there's
liable to be cuts on the arms and uh
>> which which we don't see. which we don't
see.
>> We see a large irregular wound in the
right hypochondrial region.
>> Our assassin would approach from behind,
>> right? I step from the rear, hand over
the mouth, hand goes up, I twist my body
in, knife rams up, then spinning it
around and moving it around as much as
possible to do the maximum amount of
damage before pulling the blade out and
making a run for it.
The violence of the stab wound would
have caused extreme trauma to the liver,
leaving the lady in unbearable pain.
The reason it's so be so nasty with the
liver. It's in this incredibly vascular
organ. It's got so many blood vessels
going through it to to do the job that
it does in the body. Now, here's our
weapon. Now you can imagine that if this
is penetrating through the abdominal
wall goes up into the liver and
lacerates here and he grudles it around
and he does as much damage as he
possibly can and you can see just how
vascular this liver is and all these
little bile ducts here and blood
vessels.
>> This would have been pumping out blood,
you know, at the rate of knots.
>> Incredibly messy then. I mean, a lot of
obvious signs,
>> a lot a lot of blood and guts. The guts
would have been prolapsing out the
wound. There had been enormous amount of
blood.
>> So, we have this this graphic evidence
for this vicious and violent and
terminal assault on this 30-year-old
woman. How long, you know, how long
would it have been before she died? What
would have been that sequence, do you
think?
>> I I would think it would just have been
a matter of minutes.
>> Uh if the the knife had penetrated even
deeper and and maybe taken out the major
vessels,
>> the back death would have been, you
know, in under a minute. through her
mind must have been passing all of that
family and relations and what's happened
and why it happened and just amazing
fear.
>> I would have think it would just be a
world of pain.
>> With the shocking revelation [music]
that this mummy was violently murdered,
the team now need to work out why
someone would have wanted to kill the
lady.
In a search for more clues, Joanne and
Jill are trolling through the Egyptian
archives at the Literary and
Philosophical Society Library in
Newcastle.
It has an extensive historical
collection of books, periodicals, and
newspaper reports charting the birth of
Egyptology as a science in the early
19th century.
The society hosted a public exhibition
of the mummy when it first arrived in
the country almost 200 years ago in
1821.
>> All right. Oh, what you got there?
>> Oh, lots of treats for us to look at.
>> Excellent. I've come across this one
which actually look quite interesting.
It's the reports, papers, and cataloges
of the literary and philosophical
society from [music] Newcastle upon
>> 1820 to 1821. So that's coinciding with
[music] our date. But if we have a look
through,
>> it's quite a strange book in [music] its
nature. It's more like a scrapbook
actually. And I think if we just have a
sort through
>> Oh yeah,
>> it's all handwriting.
>> Very beautiful [music] handwriting, but
then you've got small articles
>> like newspaper clipping. newspaper
clippings.
>> But the book contains more than just
newspaper articles. It's about to reveal
a very big clue.
>> Okay. Well, that's interesting.
[laughter]
>> A specimen of the cloth and cord taken
from the mummy at the literary and
philosophical society, Newcastle on 10.
I'll let you do the honors.
Oh. Oh. Here we go. Very, very careful.
>> What a result.
>> That's incredible.
>> Look at that.
>> They have kept it in a book.
>> That's fabulous.
>> 200 years. It's still very dusty.
>> It is. Yeah. Let's close it up.
>> That is Oh, I've just breathed in our
nectar. Nice.
>> [laughter and clears throat]
>> What a discovery. You don't usually make
archaeological discoveries in a library,
do you?
>> From the start of the investigation, the
team had no access to the mummy or
interior of the coffin. So, the finding
of these linen samples is a huge
breakthrough.
Tiny fragments of the linen wrappings
are cut off to be taken away for
chemical analysis in Steven's lab.
The entire imbalming process would take
around 70 days and was performed by
priests and imbalmer who had a detailed
knowledge of the human anatomy.
Some organs would be removed to avoid
decay.
The body cavity was then packed with
linen and spices before the body was
finally wrapped in many layers of linen
cloth.
[music]
It's these linen wrappings that Steven
is analyzing for their chemical [music]
fingerprint.
[music] Through GCMS gas chromatography
mass spectrometry, he will be able to
identify the chemical compounds present
on the linen sample.
The technique works on the principle
that every chemical turns to a gas at a
specific temperature. [music]
By gradually heating the microscopic
samples taken from the linen, it should
reveal the many hundreds of [music]
compounds it contains by examining the
point at which they turn to gas.
This will provide a chemical fingerprint
of each of the components used to imbalm
the [music] mummy.
Well, I've never sampled from a book
before, but it's looking quite
interesting. And what we actually have
is a ruminant fat mixed with castor
oils, a trace of chamiferin, and a trace
of beeswax.
>> Is that all?
>> Yes, [music] that's all.
>> So, nothing particularly exotic.
>> No, not really. No.
>> Well, surely [music] you'd expect a few
more exotic commodities given the status
of this woman. That sounds rather
[music] like a collection of somewhat
mundane ingredients. There does seem to
be a contradiction here between [music]
the materials used and the quality of
the cartonage we see. So I suppose the
question we should think about is is
why? [music] But you you see here um the
combustion markers which we see if
something has been very strongly heated.
So it suggests um
that someone was in a rush rather than
doing a good job.
The GCMS test has not only identified
that relatively cheap materials were
used in this imbalming, but also that
the materials used had been severely
overheated.
This correlates with the results from
the three-dimensional print of the
mummy's head, displaying large amounts
of decomposition, also indicating an
incompetent and rushed imbalming.
This is highly suspicious as the
mummification of members of Egyptian
high society was a precise and delicate
art.
No,
>> it just doesn't add up. The [music] way
she was mummified, the ingredients
aren't what one would expect given her
apparent status.
>> So, what's going on?
>> I'm not quite sure. Uh, and possibly
suggest something a little sinister.
>> [music]
>> The results of the chemical analysis
indicate that the violent stabbing of
Bakden [__] was just the [music] first
of a series of heinous crimes to be
committed against this Egyptian woman.
Professor Don Brothewell has been
conducting further analysis.
He's a leading physical [music]
anthropologist who specializes in
paleopathology
and in analyzing [music] anomalies in
the human anatomy.
Using the three-dimensional data from
the CT scan, he's identified a shocking
new development.
>> Well, I've been looking through this
area of the head and neck. So if we get
these CT scans and move through from the
face back [music] into the throat area
there first of all you can see the
tongue in the jaw and as you move back
towards the neck region
nothing then in the throat area there
there's no windpipe running there at
all.
They've slit [music] under the tongue,
removed the windpipe and so on, cleaned
it up and then inserted a large wadge of
I would think linen or something of that
sort of. I mean [music] my feeling is
that that was a decision which they took
for some carefully [music] thought out
reason and it might have in fact you
know infringed the usual policies in
terms of embarmment. So you're saying
[music] this was a premeditated
move,
>> a part of their technique?
>> Yeah. Which is something I've never seen
in any other woman. That the complete
removal of this part of the body, it
wasn't a standard part of the procedure,
was it?
>> Well, it is here.
>> Of all the human organs required after
death, the throat was one of the most
important for ancient Egyptians.
According to their belief system, the
deceased had to be able to speak his or
her own name to the god Osiris, Lord of
the afterlife,
to then be judged upon entry into the
eternal paradise for the soul.
In the eyes [music] of ancient
Egyptians, removal of the throat during
mummification would prevent this sacred
ritual from taking place.
Why take [music] out the throat, the
voice box, the the very organs that are
required, we know, to breathe again in
the next world, to speak your name in
the next world.
>> When she's there before the gods, she
physically cannot speak her name before
them. She can't identify herself. The
cartonage can't identify her. So,
>> it it does give me some some cause for
concern, I think. [snorts]
From the very beginning, this case of
the sealed coffin looked almost
impossible as the mummy investigation
team were denied any kind of access to
the body.
Against all odds and through a
combination of forensic excellence and
old-fashioned detective work, they've
built [music] an incredible picture of
who this woman was and how she died.
Based on her overbite, we [music] can
say with some confidence that she was
likely of high status.
>> Well, from the chemistry, it's certainly
possible [music] that some sort of
concealment was going on.
>> I'll go further than that. I think this
is an assassination.
There's the family,
there's the scribes, and there's the
priesthood. But it could have been
[music] any of the three.
>> Without even laying a finger on the
body, the mummy investigation team has
discovered that this woman was murdered
by a [music] savage knife attack to the
abdomen.
She was robbed of her life and even
worse in Egyptian eyes, robbed of her
passage into the next world.
This was sabotaged by a hurried
imbalming, the removal of her throat,
and the incorrect [music] inscription of
her title on the coffin.
[music]
She was murdered in real life and in the
afterlife. [music] It's been very
gratifying for me that we've actually
been able to make this person live again
in a physical sense um when we've had
absolutely no [music] access to the
body.
>> [music]
>> I think what was interesting for me was
the [music] chemistry. Um cuz it really
pointed to um a rush job. [music]
For several centuries, [music] she's
been called backed hornacked when
actually what she really was called is
back home. Merely saying that [music] is
to revive her soul.
One thing is clear. Someone with huge
power and influence hated her so much.
>> She really did live in this world of
pain for the the awful few seconds
before she passed away.
[music]
>> They killed her twice.
I know there's a fantastic story in
there. You can just tell by looking.
>> You actually can't necessarily believe
what you see.
[music]
>> The forensic process is very much
crossing things off a list.
It does really scream out, you know,
violence.
[music]
mummies. The preserved remains of
[music] people who lived long ago.
Everyone knows that the Egyptians
embarmed their dead, but for thousands
of years, South American bodies were
also mummified.
Today, these mummies give us a unique
insight into the mysterious world they
inhabited, [music]
the way it was before the Europeans
arrived.
With newly developed scientific
techniques, we can now unlock the world
they once lived in, find out who they
were, and often how they died.
[music]
Burnley's Townley Hall Museum in
Northwest England. Mummy investigator
Dr. Joanne Fletcher is an Egyptologist,
but her expertise covers mummies [music]
from around the globe.
>> Nice to meet you. Hi,
>> please come inside.
>> Excellent. [music] Thank you.
>> She's about to discover her latest
challenge.
[music]
>> It came to us in 1913 and it was sent
from Peru.
>> I must say I'm I'm very much drawn
immediately to the sort of shape of this
extraordinary skull. It's it's [music]
really really elongated.
The one thing that did [music]
interest us was this hole in the skull.
>> Oh, that's incredible. Yeah, look, it's
not just circular. It's quite square,
actually. This hole is is quite
extraordinary. Very very graphic. It
sort of it it does really scream out,
you know, violence. It's it's it's quite
awful. Is this maybe a cause of death?
The body was donated to the museum by WT
Taylor, a Burnley engineer who'd been
working on hydroelectric projects in
South America.
>> Have we any idea whereabouts [music] in
Peru Taylor obtained it?
>> Well, we think it was North Peru. North
Peru, but we're not absolutely sure.
In his notes, Taylor describes the mummy
as Chacha Poya, a culture known as the
cloud people because they lived high up
in the cloud forest, a remote part of
the highlands of northern Peru.
They were a warrior race famed for
burying their dead on perilous [music]
rock ledges high up on cliff faces.
>> What exactly are our parameters for this
investigation?
>> We're quite happy for the mummy to go
back to York.
It's very rare to have such [music]
unrestricted access to a mummy of this
kind.
>> I am very, very certain we'll be able to
give you some good results on this
because, as you say, this was once a an
individual, a human being, and we owe it
to them [music] to find out all we can
about its life and presumably its death.
York [music] University's mummy
investigation team is a
multiddisciplinary group who've been
pioneering new [music] research into
mummies for almost 10 years. Duncan Lees
is the team's forensic archaeologist.
[music] He has the technology to make
exact three-dimensional models of the
mummies they study.
>> All I'm doing is creating millions, tens
[music] of millions of accurately
surveyed points.
Jill Scott is an Egyptologist who
[music] also specializes in the study of
ancient bodies. She's the main archive
researcher on the project.
>> You don't [music] only have that out of
war wounds, you know, trauma to the
skull. You also have it through ritual
means as well.
>> Steven Buckley is an archaeological
[music] chemist. He has an international
reputation for unlocking secrets hidden
in ancient mummification techniques.
>> It's very much going into the unknown.
[music]
At this early stage of the
investigation, the team already have an
advantage. They can work on the actual
mummy [music] here at their base. And
they've nicknamed him Cloud Man.
>> I am so excited about this mummy. And
I'm sure you'll all agree it's a
fantastic example of mummification. It's
It's wonderful.
>> Mummies like Cloudman can be preserved
[music] either by natural or artificial
means. The accepted wisdom is that the
vast majority of Peruvian mummies were
naturally [music] preserved either by
being dried in cool air or in hot, dry
sand.
Our team now has the tools to [music]
determine whether this body was also
imbalmed.
You're drawn, aren't you, immediately,
to an obvious
>> an obviously unusual feature. I've never
seen [music] a skull like that. That is
just such an extraordinary shape.
They [music] think it's Chachapoa.
>> I know nothing about the Chachapooya
people. I mean, you're talking about
mountain regions. This [music] why he's
called the cloud man. I mean, what do we
know about them?
>> They are an incredible culture really
because they [music] were famed
throughout ancient Peru for their
warlike abilities. They were a
pugilistic race.
>> So, as a Chacha Poya, Cloudman would
have been one of a race of warriors who
lived between 800 and 1470 AD. They were
brutally suppressed by the Incor who
stopped at nothing to expand their
territory. But even in the midst of
battle, the Incor were said to admire
the strength and stature of the Chacha
Poya.
>> We know that they were famous for being
[music] very tall.
>> Tall. That doesn't seem to fit with this
because even though he's very tightly
bound and and in this fetal position,
the length of the [music] individual
limbs is not that great.
Are we looking at a young adult here?
>> So, it could be a younger member of
society. [music]
So, it's something to explore.
>> Steven wants to get to the bottom of why
Cloud Man's skin [music] is so pale.
>> For me, I'd be interested to know
whether there's actually anything on the
skin. [music] Uh whether we've uh got it
naturally preserved or whether there's
something that's been applied that might
be affecting the uh [music] the
appearance.
>> There is an extraordinary amount of cord
and binding on on the mummy.
These ropes are [music] something else.
I mean, far too many to have been simply
used to fasten the the hands to the head
[music] and bind the legs up.
>> Cloud man's hole in the head will also
be a key area for investigation.
>> See it from here.
>> Is it the fatal wound? I really would
like to get to the bottom of what that
hole suggests in terms of this
individual's life and his death.
>> Joanne has another resource for the team
to work with. This is um a furbound
journal from WT Taylor. Who's who's the
person that actually brought them the
mummy back in the first place?
>> Letters, photographs, [music] notes, and
maps.
>> I'd very much like you
>> I was going to say I'd be really
interested to have a look through this.
>> Besides having the book to work on, the
team will [music] also have to decipher
the clues that remain on Cloudman as
they try to find out exactly who he was
and how he [music] died. This could be
the most exciting case the team have
ever taken on.
Forensic archaeologist Duncan Lees has
begun work building a virtual model of
the mummy. He wants to stretch Cloud Man
out of his fetal position using laser
scans to give the team their first look
at the whole body.
All I'm doing is creating millions,
[music] tens of millions of accurately
surveyed points, accurately measured
points across the surface. And the
software allows you to look at that.
The laser sends out a beam onto the
mummy. And by constantly measuring the
way it bounces back, it's able to
produce an incredibly accurate
three-dimensional model.
On this mummy, you've got this sort of
pale white matte finish. And so every
single norn, [music] every single um
ripple within the tissue, all of the
cords, all of the damage in this
extraordinary shaped skull will show up
really clearly. [music] Be absolutely
beautiful data set.
The beam and receptor are so precise,
the model they generate is accurate to
within 20 microns. That's 20 millionth
of a meter, less than the thickness of
an eyelash.
Once the 3D scan is complete, Duncan
should be able to stretch the mummy out
to see how tall he was and what sort of
build he had in [music] life.
Historical researcher Jill Scott has
been reading the journal that Burnley
engineer WT Taylor brought back along
with Cloudman from his travels in Peru.
This should be able to paint a picture
of where Cloudman came from and who he
was.
There's loads of interesting stuff in
here, but it's only sort of when you get
towards the end that I'm finding any
particular references that are useful to
us for the investigation for this mummy.
>> Taylor left Burnley in 1910 and [music]
spent 3 years in Peru. Over that time,
he kept this journal which reveals a
keen interest in [music] mummies and
Inca weaponry.
And then it actually talks about him
finding [music] this mummy as well and
sort of what he had to do to get there.
Um on the early morning I with two
[music] others made preparations for
entering the deep pit. On several parts
of the passage we encountered several
petrified [music]
mummies,
human skulls and human bones.
As much as as this guy details [music]
everything here, we don't really get any
sort of concept of provenence because
all it mentioned was the fact that
[music] they've entered into mountains
down into a ravine and that there's a
hole which is about 40 ft deep. So that
that [music] could be anywhere. We can't
go to a map and pinpoint specifically
and say that that is where that mummy
was found.
Given the lack of a precise location,
Jill is going to need a Peruvian expert
to help establish Cloudman's place of
origin.
The investigation has already produced
its first results. Duncan has animated
the data from his [music] laser scan.
>> I've been working on the the laser scan
data. I put it into this visualization
package. It means that we can take this
sort of virtual tour of the mummy very
quickly. He's articulated the limbs of
what he's pretty certain now as an
adult, then taken account of any
shrinkage over the centuries.
>> But do you want to see [music] something
cool? I have we have done some work on
it. So what we've done is taken the
mummy and take, as I said, broken
[music] it down into the component
pieces of of an articulated uh adult
human. So the arms, the legs, the head,
and everything else. And what we've done
is is run this animation which shows the
mummy moving from its fetal position
into into its [laughter] standing
position.
>> Oh, that's fabulous.
>> And uh and looking at you at the end.
>> We've got a definite height here now.
We've got a 142 1.42 m. So just just
under 5 foot in height,
>> I thought.
>> Yeah. Well, yeah. Not very big. You told
me these are people famed [music] for
their pale skin, but also their height.
>> Their stature. They were noted for their
height, for their stature. Five foot.
>> Yeah. Just Well, under five foot
actually.
>> What?
>> If I brought a tape measure, I could
show you, but but certainly only up to
your sort of shoulder.
>> A
>> the Chacha Poya were known for being
tall. So, the revelation that Cloudman
was only 142 cm cast doubt on Taylor's
claim that he was Chachapoa.
With his ethnic origin in question, the
team looked to chemistry to find some
concrete answers.
Archaeological chemist Steven [music]
Buckley specializes in the chemical
analysis of mummies. Using pioneering
techniques, he works with minute samples
of the mummy [music] to establish where
it's from, how old it is, and how it
came to be preserved.
The method he uses is GCMS, gas
chromatography mass spectrometry. This
complex testing process can
>> [music]
>> identify minute quantities of chemical
compounds that have come into contact
with the body.
Steven is also taking samples [music]
which he'll send off for carbon 14
analysis to establish a date for
Cloudman. Peruvian mummies can be
anything up to 7,000 years old. So, this
will be another crucial clue to
Cloudman's identity.
Based on the mummy's pale skin, [music]
Steven has a hunch that Cloudman was
artificially preserved. And if he can
find evidence for this, it'll be
groundbreaking. [music]
>> Well, they're usually assumed to be
naturally mummified. Um, and looking at
this, there's nothing [music] to give us
any clues. But what interests me is just
to see whether whether the chemistry can
actually provide any answers on that
one.
Artificial mummification was extremely
rare in ancient Peru and would certainly
point to a high status individual.
Joanne also wants Steven to do paleo
dietary analysis to learn more about
Cloudman from the food he ate, which if
he's from the mountains should consist
of high altitude crops, traces of which
can be found in hair, bone, and body
parts. Now I have to say I've looked
very closely and I can't see any
evidence of hair or in fact fingernails
or toenails which is quite unusual for a
South American mummy. So if we wanted to
undertake paleodiatry analysis for
instance how would we go about that?
>> Well I think that could be a problem.
But I suppose another option is perhaps
to look for the um see whether the
stomach or the intestines have survived
and actually analyze the contents there.
Fortunately, [music] the team has one of
the world's leading paleopathologists on
hand. Professor Don [music] Brothewell
combines his vast medical knowledge with
a profound expertise in ancient remains.
Stevens asked Don to cut into and sample
[music] what remains of Cloudman's
internal organs to see if he can find
out about diet and evidence [music] of
possible toxins in the body. But it's
not an easy task.
There is so much decomposition we will
have to sample um fairly extensively. I
am pleased that we have permission to do
that.
>> To find out where best to operate, Don
conducts his [music] initial examination
with an endoscope normally used for
exploratory medical work.
>> I've heard of rump stakes, but rump
endoscopy [music] is
new to me. Um,
>> Don is looking for the remains of the
intestinal tract, which will give the
best information about diet, possible
toxins in the system, or infection.
>> Uh, there's some structures that are
more complete, but it's extremely
damaged
and ragged inside.
Don will cut into what he's found of the
mummy's soft tissue to obtain samples
for Steven to analyze. The trick is to
distinguish between what is useful for
the investigation and what is totally
[music] decayed matter.
It's just like old shoe leather in
parts.
That could be a part of the intestinal
wall.
>> What we need is a sort of mini hoover.
>> Yes. True.
They are also hoping to extract useful
materials from Cloudman's head.
>> You uh you're going for brain. Well, I'm
going for the what's left in terms of
tissue [music] which may be brainic.
Well, there's fly pupy there, I think,
as well.
>> As the team wait for the samples to be
processed, they concentrate on
establishing Cloudman's cultural
context.
Because ancient Peru is outside [music]
the team's direct area of expertise,
Jill Scott is meeting Dr. Nicholas
Saunders, an anthropologist specializing
in pre-Colombian Peru here at the
Bankfield Museum Halifax.
>> Take a look at this. Now, the striking
thing that we've all noticed in our
discussion is the cranial disfiguration.
[music]
So, what can you tell us about that?
Yes, it looks weird to us, but in fact
it [music] was absolutely normal in
ancient South America. U many um
civilizations def um deformed the
[music] the cranial um bones from
[clears throat] birth.
>> So we know that sometimes this was done
for ethnic identity,
>> right?
>> Tribal identity uh and sometimes it was
done as a sign of uh beauty and it was
also [music] done uh in terms of a sign
of social status.
The unnaturally long and pointed shape
of Cloudman's head is clearly a result
of cranial modification, examples of
which have been found on skulls all over
the world.
>> How did they do it?
>> Basically, they bound it with cloth uh
and sometimes with wooden boards back
and front or on the side, depending on
the exact shape they wanted. But for
them, it was an aesthetic ideal. It was
a thing of beauty.
For a 2-year period, starting shortly
after birth, Cloudman would have had his
head tightly [music] bound whilst his
skull was still malleable to shape it
into this extraordinary form. The effort
this procedure would [music] have taken
suggests Cloudman was definitely an
elite member of his society.
Working with the photographs, Nick has
found other interesting clues to
Cloudman's identity. [music]
We know from ancient Peru that prisons
of war uh and maybe shamans who cast
inappropriate spells uh were often tied
by the rope, tied by the body uh roping
one person to another [music] and
sometimes then were sacrificed. So
there's an intriguing possibility that
we can't prove at the moment that this
individual might have been a prisoner of
war.
>> Perhaps Cloudman bound with so [music]
much rope died in captivity.
To explore this possibility and to
pinpoint more about Cloudman's identity,
Jill's hoping Nick will unlock the
secrets in Taylor's diary. His first
analysis reveals some disturbing
discrepancies. the conditions that he
found these mummies in uh really relates
to the coast um rather than up in the
mountains and in the cloud forest where
he where they may have come from, but I
don't think they did. Uh examples, for
instance, would be he talks about going
40 ft down on a rope uh into a pit to
find these mummies. If he was in
Chachapo's uh region, he'd have to be
scaling a cliff for 100 ft in order to
reach them.
The chachaoya theory looks even more in
doubt. He talks that they're about
they're surrounded by sand and soil
which is clearly not going to be the
case in Chachapoas. And he also makes a
reference similarly to the mud bricks
that surround some of these mummies. Uh
again you find that all the time on the
south coast where mud bricks are
preserved. Uh in the chatapo constant
rainy area that it is they wouldn't last
5 minutes. Nick also points out that
ancient Chachapoa territory was at least
200 miles away from Lemur where Taylor
was based.
>> I think it's much more likely in fact
that he probably went for a day or two
days around the Lemur area, maybe into
the foothills of the Andes um and with a
guide found and located these things and
and took them back. So not quite as
heroic, I think, and so therefore
definitely not Chachoa.
>> This confirms the team's suspicions.
first sparked when Duncan's scan
revealed the mummy's short stature.
From the description in Taylor's
journal, it looks like his expeditions
never even got close to Chacha Pooa
territory.
I think what we're probably looking at
is uh a small coastal um culture society
maybe around about 1,200,300
AD. Um, and it's the same kind of style
of mummification that these people do
along the coast.
>> This is the investigation's first major
breakthrough. The evidence suggests that
Cloud Man is not Chacha Poya as they
originally believed. [music] He's
probably from the coast, not the
mountains, a totally different culture.
[music]
This isn't the only development in the
investigation. Stevens just had a major
setback. None of the samples Dawn took
have provided any dietary information.
This means the team's drawn a [music]
complete blank on diet, which could have
pinned down a location for Cloudman.
But he does have other important new
findings. [music]
The carbon 14 results are in, and a date
has emerged for Cloudman. 1100 AD, right
when anthropologist Nick Saunders
suspected.
This date places Cloudman firmly at a
time when no single culture [music]
predominated in Peru. Instead, small
waring tribes fought each other for
territory in a power vacuum. And given
[music] Cloudman lived at such a violent
time, the team need to test Nick's
suggestion that the excessive rope
bindings around Cloudman indicates that
[music] he was a prisoner of war who
died in captivity.
Duncan's been working with his laser
images to separate out the rope from the
rest of the body.
>> I know this looks a bit suspect and uh
but there is method to the madness. I'm
sure the thing is that we've got some
very good measurement data from the
laser scanning now and looking at the
photography, we've got a dimension for
that rope length. We've got just over
[music] 2 1/2 m of rope that we can
measure and there are areas that are
oluded, areas that we can't see. That
must add about another sort of half a
meter, maybe a bit more than that onto
the length and and it's all very well to
look at that virtually. I think we need
to get an idea of what that sort of
length of rope looks like really and how
how these [music] bindings might work.
I'd hoped that you'd help me with the
binding side of things and we we could
see what was going on. If these 3 m of
rope are enough for Duncan to tie up
Jill, this could support the theory that
Cloudman was a prisoner.
>> Right.
>> Okay. So, we've got
>> the knees and the hands were were
wrapped. [music]
>> Okay.
[music]
Mhm.
>> So, you've already got hardly any root.
>> No, I mean to me this [music] seems to
be the the sort of binding that would
have kept the body in position in death,
you know, literally to keep it position.
Yeah. Not for anything else to me.
Although 3 [music] m of rope did
initially seem like the substantial
amount needed to bind a prisoner,
Duncan's experiment has ruled out Nick
Saunders's [music] theory that Cloudman
was a bound captive.
The team decide [music] to refocus the
investigation and find out what secrets
the body itself might be hiding. They
take Cloud Man to be X-rayed.
The X-ray highlights Cloudman's [music]
cranial modification beautifully, but
can it reveal any evidence of age,
injury, or battle scars?
Armed with the images, Joanne meets up
with paleopathologist Don [music]
Brothewell to see what information he
can derive from them.
>> On that one, of course, you've got
>> the teeth aren't particularly worn.
third movers are there. I think it's
probably a very young adult, but an
adult rather than a teenager.
[music]
>> Joanne wants to determine exactly what
caused the hole in Cloudman's head.
>> I don't know. My initial thoughts, is it
a war wound? [music] So, I was wondering
if if the sort of the nature of the hole
might back that up.
>> One's immediate thought is it's ancient
surgery. But the other possibility of
course is I mean looking at it you've
[music] got to think of other things. Uh
infection can produce holes in the head.
Um tumors can produce holes in the head.
>> Joanne is not convinced [music] and
wants to know more about battle
injuries.
>> Would the sort of impact of maybe a
slingshot, high velocity slingshot on
[music] a skull such as this have
resulted in in the shape we can see
here? Do you think? I doubt it, but you
[music] should certainly consider that
as well. The thing is if you if I hit
you on the head with a hammer, then what
you get is a a sort of compressed
fracture. Your skull collapses around
the area where the hammer's impacting on
your head, but you still get the bone
there. And the only way you would to get
a hole is if in fact [music] if your
ancient surgeon then trims away the
compressed bone.
>> Would that be a possibility though?
Could we have somebody [music] that was
brought from the battlefield and then
these surgeons that we know were very
sophisticated then perform some sort
[music] of surgery on this individual?
>> A common form of cranial surgery in
ancient Peru was trepation. [music]
The surgical removal of a portion of the
skull to relieve pressure from a wound
or chronic pain.
>> It would be [music] interesting to try
and find out the various ways these
surgeries could be performed. How can we
go about [music] trying to replicate how
this was done? Because we really need to
get to the bottom of what caused it.
What do you think would be the best way
to do it?
>> Experimental work, don't you think?
>> So far, the team knows that Cloudman was
a high status young male [music] from
coastal Peru who died young in his early
20s.
Now, to pin down cause of death, [music]
they'll need to undertake two practical
experiments. To test Don's preferred
theory, they'll reproduce ancient head
surgery. To put [music] Joann's theory
to the test, they'll need to simulate a
battle injury.
Ancient Peru was a violent place full of
waring cultures fighting terrible
battles. They attacked each other with
axes, maces, and slingshots, all common
weapons.
Peruvian expert Nick Saunders has a
theory about which weapon might have
caused Cloudman's injury based on the
size and the shape of the hole.
>> This is a slingshot.
These things were used as slingshots,
but they were also worn around the head.
It should be worn into war and then
taken off and used uh and then used in
fact perhaps to [music] um cause a
dreadful damage uh and wound in somebody
else's head
>> um as well uh which may be what we have
in the mummy.
>> With a possible weapon established,
[music] the team's in a position to try
to recreate the mummy's injury. The
results might reveal what caused the
mysterious hole in Cloudman's head.
Lead investigator Joanne Fletcher is at
Flambor Beach, North Yorkshire. She
won't be satisfied until she's either
confirmed or eliminated the possibility
that the hole in the head is a war
wound.
Tom Richardson works at the Lead's
Armory and is an expert in ancient
weapons technology.
Joanne set him the challenge of
recreating the mummy's [music] injury. I
I sling at about 30 m a second.
>> Oh, that's not bad.
>> That's quite [laughter] quick. That's
quicker than fast bowlers in cricket
bowl that.
>> And of course, they bounce the ball on
the on the pitch before it hits the
batsman.
>> So, we're actually looking at something
that that could do a lot of damage. I
mean, something going that quick. I
mean, it's sort of
>> like an ancient version of a bullet from
a gun, really, isn't it?
>> Yeah, absolutely. It's
it's very difficult [music] to sling in
a non-lethal way.
To test the lethal power [music] of a
slingshot, they brought along a pig's
head to be the target.
Joanne also has a speed [music] gun to
determine just how fast Tom can sling
at.
They take their positions. If Tom can
hit the pig's [music] head with
sufficient power, he could prove that a
slingshot might have caused the mummy's
injury.
>> Oh, [music] 65. Tom's getting readings
of 65 mph or 30 m a second, [music] but
he's still way off target. Of course,
the problem with all this is accuracy.
>> Well, how would they have actually
deployed these in ancient times?
>> Rather than having a [music] single
slinger sniping away, you have to think
of a whole group of say 500 slingers
raining stones down on a whole group of
people.
>> So, kind of like aerial bombardment.
>> Exactly. So,
Finally, he's starting to home in on the
pig's head.
>> Got it.
[music]
>> Although the slingshot hit the head at
65 mph, it didn't even pierce the skin.
Right now, [music] Joanne's battle
injury theory is not looking very
convincing.
Meanwhile, forensic archaeologist Duncan
Lees wants to explore how ancient
surgery might have created the injury by
trapanning a pig's skull. Royal Navy
surgeon commander Mike Edwards is
particularly wellqualified to conduct
this procedure. The last time I did
anything closely approaching this was in
a tent just outside Bazer in 2003.
I was uh called to um operate on a Royal
Marine who'd been hit by some trapnel.
>> Right. Back in ancient Peru, people were
also being trapanned for battle
injuries.
>> One of the the main reasons for doing it
may well have been trauma, right?
>> We usually be blunt trauma from clubs
and slingshots [music] and um the rate
of skull fracture would be high.
>> So in essence, it's a sort of
battlefield medicine. Okay.
>> But there'll be also non-traumatic
reasons for doing it. Say
>> for relief of epilepsy.
>> Okay. uh if they had a brain tumor that
was growing and they had increasing
headaches, uh feeling might have been to
let the evil spirits out.
>> People have been trapanned in countless
cultures across the world [music] since
at least 7,000 BC.
>> I think there are even modern
extrapolations of this with lunatics
that think they can reach [music] heaven
by uh opening their skull to the
atmosphere.
It's quite likely that many of those
trapanned in ancient Peru were also
seeking spiritual awakening rather than
relief from a head injury.
For this experiment, Mike will be using
a replica of an ancient surgical
instrument, one that might have been
used in 12th century Peru. Talk me
through the tools that you brought,
Mike.
>> Now, this is this is an obsidian blade.
>> Okay. Volcanic glass. Volcanic glass.
>> And it seems incredibly sharp down the
edge here.
>> Oh, it is incredibly sharp. And I would
say this would equate to something like
a scalpel which we have here.
>> Right. Okay.
>> So we can see that you [music] know in
fact you know this may even be sharper
than the scalpel.
>> Yeah.
>> If Cloudman's injury was caused by
trepation, this kind of [music] obsidian
blade is probably what they would have
used to cut into his head.
>> Mike wants to use this tool to see if he
can recreate the same kind of hole in a
pig's head.
>> I'm just going to hope that this is
sharp enough. Okay.
Oh, fantastic. Once we're through the
first layer of skin, it does go through
a lot easier.
>> So, this needs a bit of pressure. If I
made this cut, so if this was alive,
this would be bleeding like anything.
>> Okay.
>> I think it would be possible to lose
about four pints of blood from a a
severe scalp laceration.
[music]
>> It's absolutely amazing. In ancient
Peru, there's evidence that red hot
metal would have been used to sear the
blood vessels and stem the bleeding. I'm
just going to make a cut here now.
If he didn't pass out from the pain,
Cloudman would have been conscious
throughout the operation.
>> I've scored in a circular way around
here, you can see, and I've just gone
through the outer table of the skull.
And I'm feeling I'm just getting to the
inside. And my plan is to keep doing
this until I get through the skull. And
what I don't want to do is I don't want
to go so deep that I go into the brain.
This is just great. What a great tool.
I don't think I could get such a good
result even with a modern chisel or or a
scalpel.
After 45 minutes, Mike's close to
penetrating the pig's skull.
This is going to come very soon.
>> I can see movement on the trapan.
>> I think there is most definitely
movement there. And if I just lift
that away. Oh, that is fantastic.
>> So, so we've got the trapan piece and
then and then
>> the hole and the brain underneath, but
with no damage. No, it looks to me like
it's all intact.
>> Using a stone age [music] tool, Mike has
managed to trapan a skull without even
damaging the membrane surrounding the
brain.
The team has now explored what might
have caused Cloud Man's head injury in
two ways.
Before the results can be evaluated,
[music] the two damaged pig skulls need
to be x-rayed.
While Joanne and Duncan have been
experimenting with pig's heads, Steven's
been working through the thousands of
pages of chemical data generated by the
samples he's taken from the mummy.
To conclude [music] the experiments,
Joanne returns to Don Brothewell to see
if the X-ray evidence supports her
theory that the hole was originally a
war wound.
>> The surgery here and then down here
we've got the results of the
>> [music]
>> uh slingshot.
>> I think your slingshot experiments you
might have damaged the skull just very
superficially.
Well, I think uh your experimental work
here with trepation [music]
is beautiful and um convinces me
actually that what you have here is
trepation without any doubt. [music]
>> Don's conclusive trepation caused the
hole in Cloudman's head. [music]
>> So, was my day on the beach completely
wasted?
>> Your day on the beach was lovely. I hope
the weather was fine. the paddle. But as
far as this is concerned, forget it.
>> Do you think this was successful
surgery?
>> Oh, it certainly because [music] on the
X-ray you can see that there's a lot of
healing around the hole.
>> So, we can say this wasn't immediately
fatal.
>> Oh, no, no, no.
>> And it wasn't the cause of death. So,
[music] this individual lived how long
would you say?
>> Well, it's so well healed up that you
can't really sort of predict how long,
but [music] he lived many months.
Cloudman survived his surgery, but given
he died at such a young age, could
having such major surgery [music] have
left him open to infection.
Far from confirming cause of death, the
team's experiments have only raised more
questions, there are no clues as to why
Cloud Man was trapanned. Was it because
he suffered from severe head pains or
epilepsy? Or did [music] he, as people
have done throughout the centuries, open
his head up voluntarily to be closer to
his gods?
>> Joanne has called a team meeting.
>> If there's no cause of death, it's it's
a question of where do we go from here?
Really,
>> I mean, I don't really share the
pessimism. I mean, the forensic process
[music]
is very much crossing things off a list.
You know, there there are very few
things that you can say for sure.
There's a lot of things that you can
cross off. And we've the work that we've
done so far is crossing things off that
list.
I know there's a fantastic story in
there. [music] You can just tell by
looking at him. He's he's a fantastic
mummy. And I so want to do this justice.
So, I think maybe I am sort of uh
[music]
being a little despairing. Yeah.
Pessimistic. Yeah.
>> The science. There's so much more
science still to do. So much that we
haven't looked at. Glaringly [music]
obvious things in front of us. I mean,
there there must be answers already
coming out of the science that you're
doing, Steen, as well. [music] What sort
of stage are we at with your stuff?
>> The mummy has been smoked.
really.
>> So, as part of the mummification
process,
>> yeah,
>> this is a major revelation. Steven's
hunch was spot on. He's found out that
the mummy's pale skin color was produced
artificially. The body was smoked as a
method of preservation.
>> There's nicotine there with tobacco
[music] leaf, it would appear. Yeah.
>> Oh, that that's pretty shattering
actually.
>> So, mummified certainly a surprise. A
surprise perhaps, but unfair surprise as
well, I think. You know, the scientists
will come up with the right stuff. Yeah,
you
>> fantastic news. This [music] is really
big, isn't it? I mean, that that's sort
of the first time I know of of this
definitely being found on a mummy.
>> Yeah, it's quite nice.
>> Well, that's the understatement [music]
of the year, isn't it?
>> Artificial mummification in Peru is
virtually undocumented. [music]
This has to suggest that Cloudman was a
member of the elite. Smoking the body
would have helped to preserve it by
keeping out insects. [music]
But obtaining the tobacco for this
procedure would have been a massive
task. It must have been one of the
rarest and most precious commodities
since the nearest [music] tobacco was
grown in the Amazon basin at least 400 m
away. It would have required weeks of
traveling to bring it back to Cloudman's
coastal region.
As the results come in, Steven realizes
that he's on the verge of a major
scientific discovery. He's found
chemical substances which show that not
only was Cloud Man smoked, he was also
imbalmed.
>> On the head you have a plant wax which
is actually very characteristic and
[music] it's comes from candela wax from
Mexico. But in contrast on the legs
you've [music] got an insect wax which
is unusual.
>> Cloud man's legs were treated with
insect wax, his body with a balsom tree
resin and his head with a plant wax.
first and foremost [music] as
preservatives to prevent water and fungi
from entering and destroying the body.
But what makes Steven's results so
intriguing [music] is that these
substances weren't readily available in
coastal Peru. The candilla wax found on
the head was derived [music] from a
small shrub which is still used today in
beauty products. It was sourced an
amazing 2,000 m away on another
continent, [music] Mexico in North
America. Using these highly praised
products on his body means Cloudman must
[music] have been an extremely important
person. Such lavish attention suggests
the equivalent of a state funeral. If I
was asked to speculate on who this
individual might be from the science,
certainly this is a high status
individual. He's been treated with
substances from coming from really long
distances. So, [music]
uh this would have been a very expensive
process. So this is someone who
had a great deal of wealth um and status
uh and was someone quite special.
To understand [music] what these
substances symbolized in ancient
Peruvian burial rituals, Steven needs to
consult a specialist.
He sends his lab results to the team's
Peruvian expert, Nick Saunders.
Steven's scientific discoveries are
startling, but [music] won't fully
unlock the secret of Cloudman's role in
life unless they're put into their
proper cultural context.
Steven's faith has paid off.
Anthropologist Nick Saunders has
examined the chemical findings and
emailed some astounding conclusions.
>> Plenty to look at. Uh, one thing I
noticed is the um, the recipe you
describe is really a microcosm of the
herbal world. Each element representing
a physical and symbolically important
substance.
>> That's pretty good.
>> Yes. [music] Look, it shows us that
these ancient peoples had a philosophy
of the body where different substances
and varying [music] combinations were
regarded as symbolically appropriate for
the head and legs. That's exactly right,
isn't it? That's that's exactly what the
science is [music] telling us.
>> Yeah.
The embalming process clearly had huge
symbolic significance. Each [music] part
of Cloudman was deliberately treated
with a different substance. His head
with plant wax,
his body with tree resin,
and his legs with insect wax. [music]
The presence of insect wax on our mummy
might indicate he could have been a
sheaman or a sorcerer who [music] used
these creatures for curing illness. in
life and was now in turn protected in
death by their spiritual essence.
Brilliant.
>> Yeah,
>> this is great. [music] This is the hard
science coming together with cultural
history.
>> Yeah, I mean it's great to see the uh
the science making sense.
>> This is a huge breakthrough. The
evidence suggests that Cloudman was a
shaman, a tribal witch doctor who cast
spells and communicated with the spirit
world.
Insects had a divine quality in ancient
Peru as bringers of disease. They were
also used in preventative medicine.
It's possible a shaman would have
consumed certain insects with
psychedelic properties as part of his
ritual communication with the gods.
[music]
And there's more.
The nicotine in the body and mass may
have been partly from the use of it
during life. So if he was a sheaman
using this stuff, but also from the
mommy's postmortem ritual treatment
deemed appropriate for a shaman.
There are even tobacco shamans in
Venezuela today. A tobacco shaman. What
a an amazing concept.
>> That's fantastic.
>> It's [music] excellent. I mean, I was I
was sure of the uh of the science of the
chemistry, but it's actually nice to see
that this actually does make some sense.
>> Steven's discoveries both on tobacco
smoking and Cloudman's chemical
imbalming will reshape scientific
opinion on South American mummies.
After weeks of investigation, [music]
the team have finally established who
Cloudman was in life. A sheaman, a high
status and powerful religious [music]
figure. This was a man born around 1100
AD in the coastal region of Peru,
[music] close to where the capital city
of Lemur stands today. At birth, his
head was bound into this extraordinary
shape like the [music] other elite
members of his society. And
>> sometimes it was done as a sign of
beauty and it was also done uh in terms
of a sign of [music] social status.
>> But Cloudman had a greater destiny than
his contemporaries. He only lived to his
early 20s. I think it's probably a very
young adult, but an adult rather than a
teenager.
>> But in his short life, it seems he rose
to be a shaman, a holy man with a direct
link to the spirit world. And perhaps he
was [music] trapanned to open up his
head to commune with his gods.
>> Feeling might have been to let the evil
spirits out. We'll never be sure how he
died, but given the lack of other trauma
[music] on his body, it's likely he died
from an illness or infection, possibly
as a long-term side effect of his
trapanning. At death, [music] his high
status was reflected in the
extraordinary care with which his body
was preserved with waxes brought from
thousands of miles [music] away. This
would have been a very expensive
process. So, this is someone who had
great deals of wealth.
So we've gone from the cloud man to
tobacco shaman.
>> Thanks to the embarmming skills of his
community, he has not decayed like
[music] almost all his contemporaries.
This expert and rare preservation has
allowed the team to breathe life back
into this individual and unravel the
secrets sealed in his mummified body for
almost [music] a thousand years.
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat. [music]